Rosemary Farrar Papers, 1930-1986
Mortimer Rare Book Room
Rosemary Farrar Papers
1930-1986
Farrar, Rosemary
270
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
Contains some manuscripts and published works by Rosemary Farrar. Also has an extensive run of the annual volumes of The Poetry Society of Georgia (1944-1984).
Rosemary Farrar was born in Boston, Massachusetts on July 8, 1915, the daughter of Frederick C. and Freda F. Kelsey Farrar. They moved to Alford, Massachusetts, in 1921, and it was there that she lived most of her life. Farrar attended school in Dalton and Great Barrington, Massachusetts, and graduated in 1932 from the Searles High School of Great Barrington.
Farrar was employed as a bookkeeper and accountant during her working career in a Ford automobile agency that successively went by the names Whalen & Kasther Agency, Mahaiwe Motors and then Whittaker Ford.
Farrar started writing while still in high school and continued to write poetry all of her adult life. Her poems were published in various publications, including the New York Times, the Christian Science Monitor, the Washington Post and Yankee magazine. In 1981 her book of poetry Voices Will Ring was published. She was a member of the Poetry Society of America, the Poetry Society of Georgia, the Poetry Society of Virginia and the Massachusetts State Poetry Society, as well as an associate member of the Academy of American Poets. She was also a member of St. James' Episcopal Church in Great Barrington and a longtime member of the Alford Garden Club.
Rosemary Farrar died on March 2, 1986 in the Willowood Nursing Home in Great Barrington, Massachusetts.
The Rosemary Farrar Papers consists of some manuscript copies of her poems and a collection of publications containing her poetry. Also included are some reviews of her only book of poetry, Voices Will Ring.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. MANUSCRIPTS
II. PUBLISHED POETRY
III. OTHER PUBLICATIONS
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
The Rosemary Farrar papers were a gift of Elizabeth Rose in 1986. Ms. Farrar left the contents of this collection to Mrs. Rose.
Farrar, Rosemary.; Poets, American-20th Century-Biography-Sources; Farrar, Rosemary; Poetry Society of Georgia
- I. MANUSCRIPTS
  The manuscripts include some school writings, manuscripts of published and unpublished poems and the manuscript of Farrar's book Voices Will Ring, along with reviews. The manuscripts are arranged in chronological order.
- II. PUBLISHED POETRY
  This series consists of a collection of books, magazines and newspaper clippings containing poems of Rosemary Farrar. The printed versions of Farrar's poems are arranged in chronological order.
- III. OTHER PUBLICATIONS
  This series consists of a collection of books, pamphlets and annual publications with which Farrar was associated. The publications are arranged in chronological order.
- SERIES I. MANUSCRIPTS
  - History, vol. 1-2, School writings on historic topicsundated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Music score book, containing exercises and compositions undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts (typescript originals and/or carbon copies) of published poems, with notations as to where published 1951-1971, undated, Includes the poems: Christmas Eve, Simple Song, Leisure, Special Grace, The Grey Squirrel, The Under-Mountain Road, Golden Anniversary, Twilight Snow, The Cocks Have Crowed (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts (mostly carbon copies, but also typescript originals) of 30 unpublished poems (not in Voices Will Ring)undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Little Yellow Cats (carbon copy), an unfinished short story (3 copies) and handwritten drafts 1972-1976, undated, Verso: Whisper, a poem published in 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript (carbon copy) of Voices Will Ring undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes and copies of letters related to the publication of Voices Will Ring 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Folder of reviews on Voices Will Ring1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Rosemary Farrar or Elizabeth Rose on Voices Will Ring 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Mary Shepard White, 27 Jul 1983; from Luther Starnes, 30 Nov 1983; from Elizabeth J. Hodges, 11 Aug 1986 1883, 1986 (Box 1)
- SERIES II. PUBLISHED POETRY
  - The Grey Squirrel (in The Paebar Anthology of Verse: Third Series. New York: The Paebar Co., 1935, p. 17) 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rustic Paradox (in American Women Poets 1937. Edited by Margery Mansfield. New York: Henry Harison Poetry Publisher, 1937, p. 37) 1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miss Caroline (in Kaleidograph 9 Dec 1937): no. 8, p. 10)1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Twilight Snow (in Yankee 5 (Mar 1939): no. 3, p. 29) 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Land Not Rained Upon (in The Writer 52 (Sep 1939): no. 9, p. 275) 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Cocks Have Crowed (in Voices: A Quarterly of Poetry 103 (Autumn 1940, p. 41)1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Cocks Have Crowed (in The Poetry Society of America Anthology. New York: The Fine Editions Press, 1946, p. 57) 1946 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Counsel (in This is my America. Washington, D.C.: The Washington Poetry, 1946, p. 37) 1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Lilac (in mimeographed pamphlet of poems, p. [12] Also another similar pamphlet of poetry.undated) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Folder of seven poems published in newspapers that had previously been published 1940 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- SERIES III. OTHER PUBLICATIONS
  - Poems for Every Mood. Complied by Harriet Monroe and Morton Dauwen Zabel. Racine, Wis.: Whitman Publishing Co. 1933, Inscribed by Rosemary Farrar to her mother, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Poetry Society of Georgia [annual volume]. Holdings are: 20 (1944), 23 (1947), 30 (1954)-32 (1956), 49 (1973)-60 (1984)1944, 1947, 1954, 1956, 1973, 1984, Farrar had poems published in: v. 23, p. 18: Golden Anniversary; v. 52, p. 28-29: Waterlude; v. 53, p. 30-31: Property Settlement (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Poetry Society of America 66th Annual Dinner: program 22 April 1976, Also newspaper article on one of the honorees: Margery Mansfield (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Lyric 57 (Fall 1977): no. 4 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Poetry Society of Virginia [membership list]1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Yearbook of the First Resistance Chapter, National Society Daughters of the American Revolution 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Poetry Society of America Membership List 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Alford Garden Club 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)